In this video, we're going to have a quick look at why genetics were introduced and how do we use them?
Right, we have been using them obviously with collections for just one reason and that's the
overwhelming reason really. So what happened before Java 5 was released,
that's quickly going in the collections package again. I'll just have a new class, I'll say
generics here. So here we go, as you see on my screen, love the mean method. And now let's use
any collection, right? For example, let's go on and use an analyst. And I'll say less to new.
Just ignore the warnings for now, because you know that I'm not using generics, the angular
brackets, right? And that's why there are warnings. But this list, before Java 5.0 was a
heady using a list or any collection for that matter, it could store, it could handle any type
of data. So at first, in the beginning, that looks a great feature, right? That looks an
advantage over areas, which were always type restricted. So what you did is you did something like
you said, less today and any object now, right? Not just string or integer because object is the
superclass of every class in Java. And it can hold any, any object there, right? So we get hold,
let's say the integer 56. And you will be surprised to see how is 56 as an integer story.
This is through Java 5, another feature, which was introduced in Java 5, that was
auto boxing and unboxing, right? This in primitive value is it is automatically converted into
its wrapper class object, right? We call that auto boxing. And when a wrapper object is automatically
converted into its primitive equivalent, it's called unboxing. Remember the word that important
word here is automatic. If you do it, then it's not automatic boxing, right? It has to be not
automatically. So now this is stored, you can go ahead and do, let's start a string as well.
And that works, remember before Java 5, where having a look at how things work in the pre-java
5, well, without generic spin there. And then you could have said, let's start add, let's say my new
generic, a more object as well, kind of of this class. And it was able to hold that as well.
And then I said, let's just ignore all these warnings. I can even store a boolean, all right.
So now at the surface, things look very good. And you go ahead and just print it out
by the same list. And we should get it in insertion order because you know now that
error list maintains the insertion order, but it's not sorted. So we'll just run this.
And off we go, we get 56, what an object of generic is demo and then false, right?
So in the order in which you inserted them. Now, let's say I have to traverse them with an enhanced
for loop, or I have to get the value at an index, let's do that. So let's say list or get perfectly
fine, index of three, or let's say three, okay. And we know 0, 1, 2, 3, let's say we would take it in a
boolean. Let's say boolean value, you get immediately an error. And why is that? Can you guess that?
And that is because you added an object, right? Or all of these are objects, right? But generic
objects, right? So how about this? It says that required time Boolean provided object, right? Because
these sometimes we added integers, other times we ended strings, custom class objects,
Boolean. So they are added into this list as the generic object, that is an object of that class
object of the capital O, right? Which is the super class of every class in Java, that's why it's
allowed. And once you try to get it, it is returned as an object, it doesn't know there is a boolean
there, but only you know it, right? And currently because you have a look at all of this class,
that's why you can go ahead and try to try cast it. And it works. But what happens when you don't know
what is in the list and that's the majority of the situation because you'll be getting a list,
that's it. The values won't be coming from a database, from an API, from another class, you won't
know what is in the list. So how can you safely convert it? You can't, right? So this is painful,
and not certain to work, right? This type of casting approach and you'd have to do that for
anything that you get out of it. So that's the first problem. The second problem is let's say I do a
for loop. And I say I have to get the values out of this list, but this time what is that you would
define the type of this value earlier, when I had a string only less, I put the variable type to
string, when I had an integer only less, I put the variable type to integer, when I had a
generic demo only less, I put the variable type to generic demo, but what would I put here, right?
If we just say, teacher error, right, say says that required object provided integer,
and that's why you would have to say option because it takes everything. And then when you say
a system or don't bring it in, now I want to call whack dot to lowercase, right? So I'll say
why not to lowercase doesn't work because again, while is a type of object inside object,
there is no method called to lowercase, it's only inside string. So again, type casting,
you would do it like this. That's how it works, but it would fail at runtime because the first object
that would be fetched out from this list is an integer, and you're trying to convert an integer
into a string that they have no relationship in between. That's why this would fail for the first time,
so you would have to put in that instance of test and then check it and then convert it
too painful, too verbose, right? So these are the glaring disadvantages we get with
pre-generics, reach out of five quotes. You run this, we hear expert in error. First,
prints out everything that is, then gets the Boolean out, then for the first instance in the loop,
says exception in thread main job line dot class class exception. Now you should know when does
the compiler throw us a class class exception is when you're trying to convert the wrong types,
it says integer cannot be cast string, right? Those are the problems, right? And that is where
generics came in and just removed all of that, right? It said, define your list first. Do you
want it to hold integer strings or generics demo your choice? I'll say string, right? And diamond syntax,
that's it. Now in error here, you cannot enter an integer into a string or a list. You cannot enter
a generics demo object interesting. So a list, you cannot enter a Boolean object into a
general string only list, right? Doesn't work only this works as you're seeing. Just comment this.
Let's add one more, I'll say list, right? And let's say shooting. And now, see, this won't work
obviously. And it's not even required because the moment you try to get it, see, you'll just say,
you know, when you're sure what is going inside, you're 100% certain what would come out,
and that means if I say list or get of one, I know it's always going to be a string.
See, no type casting required, no fingers crossed. This would always work. It would get a string,
I'm taking into a string, and then here, not object, just string, and this will always work
type casting no longer required. See, you run this.
We should get what we are looking for, right? So that is the idea would teach we get with
generics. And this was the overwhelming reason to introduce generics was for collections,
right? But sometimes you would define, you can go ahead and do other things with generics,
but one of them is defining your custom class like this, for example, let's say over class,
I'll just call it my, and then you define a generic parameter right here, right? Or what I'll say
is I'll define it here. See, I'll say E, okay, and define this E right here. Okay, and then what
happens is whatever you pass when you create an object of this class, whatever this E is,
a drawing time, it would be decided. There was a similar concept such as templates in C++,
this is generics in Java, for creating custom parameters, custom classes, right? So that is you're
saying whatever I pass at a drawing time, that is what E would become, right? If I pass integer,
this ref would become a type integer. If I pass string, it would become a save string. If I pass
a custom class object, this would become a type of that custom class, and then go ahead and
read custom classes, sorry, constructors, I'll say E, if, and you'll see. Like you do this
or type equal to graph, you can even have methods, I'll say, I'll click E, which will be the return type
now, get graph, and you'll say this dot, there, please return that. You can even have setters,
I'll say public, white, saved, there, take an argument, type E, and then you'll say,
let's start, absolutely wonderful stuff this, this E is not known until you pass it later on,
and in different situations, this E becomes different, sometimes it becomes an integer,
all through the class, then it becomes a string, it becomes a floated becomes your custom
class object as well. Let me just try to give you an example, a brief example here, see.
Now, when you try to click create an object, I'll say my seeds, seeds, pass an argument,
and I'll say, this time, it's an integer, I'll say, let's call it OBJ,
create an object, new, my timer, syntax, and pass that, hey, I say 560, that becomes the ref,
and now, see, everywhere down the line, this becomes an integer, integer, integer,
integer, integer, it takes an integer, gets an integer, and sets an integer as well, right,
and a demo of that would be, let's say a sound, I'll say OBJ, right, let's try, see, returns
an integer, do you see that, right, you run this, say, 560, so that is another use case of using
generics, but as I said, the overwhelming situation is for using these collections, and that's how
they've changed collections, because sometimes this is the same error list, it behaves as a string
only list, it behaves at other times as an integer, it behaves at another time as a double only
list, or a custom class object only list, how, because thanks to the generic parameters, whatever
you pass, that e behind the scenes, take takes the place of that.